so help me flesh out some of these
contradictions i think that on the whole
it's really good that we have
national whistleblower appreciation day
and
i would say overall that i'm glad that
there's someone like
senator chuck grassley who has pushed
forward
and stood up for at least the modest
whistleblower protections that we've
been able to win
both chuck grassley and ron wyden have
been
two of the only senators who stand up on
whistleblower issues in the past 10
years
they're one of the only two or three
senators you can point to
who have challenged the way an insider
threat program
has been ruled out and instituted
in the fbi and other intelligence
agencies
that being said the resolution for
establishing whistleblower appreciation
day
is incredible to me because it contains
um so many caveats i i'd like to just
take a moment to
read it to you so you can see um
uh the resolution they passed for
this year this particular year from
chuck grassley
what he decided uh needed to be in here
was this
this very clear-cut statement i don't
resonate with you because
he's excluding you from whistleblower
appreciation day
it says in the resolution whereas it is
the public policy of the united states
to encourage
in accordance with federal law and
consistent with the protection
of classified information including
sources and methods of detection of
classified information
honest and good faith reporting of
misconduct fraud
misdemeanors and other crimes to the
appropriate
authority at the earliest time possible
now therefore be it and then it goes on
to outline
what they're doing but as i'm pointing
out there there are these disqualifiers
for whistleblowers yes
there always are uh you know chuck
grassley
is probably the best friend that
whistleblowers have on capitol hill and
that's not
saying a lot uh he's certainly not my
friend
um chuck grassley's not done anything
for me a couple members of congress had
my own congressman at the time jim moran
lloyd doggett of texas senator john
mccain they were
all great and i appreciated the help
very much
chuck grassley was not a help and chuck
grassley speaks at the national
whistleblower day
lunch in every single year oftentimes
another congressman will stop by and
wave and you know
bask in his applause but this year the
speaker
is michael horowitz who's the justice
department's inspector general
i wrote a piece in consortium news a
couple of days ago in which i said that
i was boycotting
the the event this year because it's
horowitz and horowitz in my view is a
fraud
i have a friend an fbi whistleblower
named darren jones and darren jones has
gone through
a nightmare for the past eight years
plus thanks in large part to michael
horowitz
and i don't think we should be honoring
the man i think we should be criticizing
him and demanding
that he respect whistleblower rights
which he doesn't
and the other thing that i want to add
here to this broadcast before we get on
to
celebrating individual whistleblowers is
that i'll
never forget that chelsea manning was
convicted on national whistleblower
day that she was uh that
uh on the same day that we
were celebrating um you know there's
there's this case
that involves um a soldier who stood up
to torture
i believe is the actual case that sparks
uh that that if you read chuck
grassley's
um establishment of the national
whistleblower appreciation day it goes
back
to the time period of the revolutionary
war
so that's the case and
on the same day on on july 30th
that's the day that the u.s military
court at fort meade
found chelsea manning guilty of
violating
the espionage act which i think just
brings out one of the more glaring
contradictions and i think
you know to you i say what are your
thoughts about how
there really aren't any and i think
to flip this around it's really on us to
do something to agitate and try to win
more protections but there's no
mechanism for
people like you to blow the whistle on
war
and war crimes and malfeasance in war
zones
and it's so easy to
be found and labeled a traitor
because there's not very good channels
set up for
anybody who wants to expose that kind of
waste fraud and abuse
right um senator roy blunt of missouri
called me a traitor uh and he wasn't the
only one who called me a traitor but
you're exactly right and you point out
exactly what the problem is
the problem is that the whistleblower
protection law
says that you have to uh report
malfeasance that is waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety
through channels and through channels
means
to your boss to the inspector general
maybe to the general counsel
finally to the oversight committees that
doesn't work
tom drake the nsa whistleblower went
through channels
went to the oversight committees went to
the inspectors general
and was rewarded with nine felony counts
including seven counts of espionage
now the case fell apart but not before
he was ruined financially and personally
if you work in the intelligence
community if you work
in the military you can't go through
channels because it's your channels that
are violating the law
it's the oversight committees who are
complicit
in it for example i wanted to blow the
whistle
on the torture program i worked in the
cia's counterterrorism center
my bosses created the torture program
the inspector general ignored the
torture program
the general counsel legally approved
the torture program and the oversight
committees secretly funded the torture
program
so the only way but the only place for
me to go
was to the media and that's true of
many most maybe uh national security
whistleblowers of course
when you go to the media you take your
future in your hands
because you're probably looking at an
espionage charge or multiple espionage
charges
even though that's not espionage that's
what the obama administration
did they set a precedent by charging
people with espionage for speaking with
the media
so it's it's very dangerous you know
with some regularity i get calls from
people who are considering becoming
whistleblowers and i always tell them
think long and hard before you make this
decision
because your friends are going to walk
away from you your co-workers
will never speak to you again in many
cases
it'll split your family it may wreck
your marriage
you'll never ever work in government
again
you'll probably never work in corporate
america either because of the background
investigation necessary
so you have to really believe in your
heart
that you are doing the right thing it's
the right thing for you
it's the right thing for the country
it's in defense of the constitution
and then act and the other thing that i
always tell them is don't make the
mistake that i made
and be reactive be proactive
and engage an attorney who specializes
in whistleblower defense
before you go public then at least you
can
partially control the narrative